Guide to the Walter and Ruth Marie Taylor Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Walter and Ruth Marie Taylor Papers
1923-1954
RG 251
Yale University Divinity School Library
2
(3 boxes)
Letters, writings, and photographs document the life and work of Walter Taylor as an Episcopal missionary architect based in Wuhan, Central China from 1923 to 1927. Taylor's long distance courtship of his future wife Ruth Marie Smith, her eventual voyage to China to marry him in 1926, and their life in China during a politically turbulent time are well documented.
Taylor, Walter Andrews, 1899-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Kenneth W. Taylor and Mark Taylor.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Biographical / Historical
Walter Andrews Taylor (1899 - 1963) graduated from Ohio State University in 1922, a member of Tau Beta Pi. He was appointed by the Episcopal Church to serve as an architect in China. Enroute, while traveling in England, he met his future wife Ruth Marie Smith, who eventually joined him in China in 1926 to be married. Taylor was based in Wuchang [Wuhan], Hubei province, in central China from 1924 until 1927. When the 1926 Siege of Wuchang forced the evacuation of the missionaries, the Taylors stayed at the Kuling Mountain missionary retreat through the siege but were ordered to leave China in 1927. Taylor and his wife returned to the U.S. where he worked in the office of Hobart Upjohn, NYC and was a Lecturer at Columbia University. From 1936 to 1946 he was a Professor in the Deparatment of Architecture of Syracuse University. From 1946 to 1959 he was Director of the Department of Education and Research at American Institute of Architects. From 1959 to 1963 he was Dean of the School of Architecture, Ohio University.
Scope and Contents
These papers tell the story of a young missionary architect sent to China by the Episcopal Church. Enroute he meets a young American woman in England and they eventually begin a long distance courtship that leads to her coming to China to be married. Though the time period served by Walter Taylor in China was brief, his letters and writings provide valuable insight into missionary life and his work as an architect. Series I includes Family Correspondence - letters written by Walter and Ruth Marie to their families, and to each other. Series II includes a small amount of non-family correspondence, including letters to/from fellow missionaries. The Writings of Series III include published articles by Taylor about missionary architecture in China, as well as his five-year diary covering the period of his service in China. Series IV, Personal Items and Memorabilia contains various clippings and ephemera that illustrate the events and lifestyle of the missionaries. Series V includes photographs not only of the Taylors but also of some of the buildings he designed.
Filed in the first folder are two copies of a DVD containing scans of letters, documents, and photos included in the collection.
Arrangement
I. Family Correspondence, 1923-1926
II. General Correspondence, 1926-1927
III. Writings, 1924-1954
IV. Personal Items and Memorabilia, 1923-1926
V. Photographs, 1924-1926, no date
Missions -- China; Taylor, Walter Andrews, 1899-; Episcopal Church -- Missions -- China
- Family Correspondence, Series I
  Scope and Contents
  Filed in the first folder are two copies of a DVD containing scans of letters, documents, and photos included in the collection.
  - Walter Taylor to his parents
    - Letters describe Walter's travels enroute to his new position as architect in China, including stay in England to study cathedrals, where he met Ruth Marie Smith at Warwick Castle., 1923 May - Oct (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Including regarding stops in Paris and Italy enroute to China, beginning work at Boone University in Wuchang [Wuhan], 1923 Oct - Dec (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Time spent in Peking [Beijing] attending language school, then working and traveling with base at Boone University, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Including regarding work and social life, anti-Christian activities by Chinese; WT confronted by students; vacation and travels for work, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Including regarding plans to marry Ruth Marie Smith; Ruth Marie appointed to mission and will arrive in China in August after meeting Taylor family enroute; marriage on August 26; Siege of Wuchang in fall of 1926 leads to Taylors' evacuation and return to U.S., 1926 - 1927 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Walter Taylor to Ruth Marie's mother
    - Prior to their marriage, WT writes to assure Ruth Marie's mother of his love and her safety in coming to China, 1926 Jun (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Ruth Marie Smith Taylor to/from family
    - Letters to her mother during trip to Europe when she met WT; letters written enroute to China and after marriage, 1923 Sep - 1926 Oct (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Letters to/from Taylors regarding engagement and welcome to family; invitations to visit enroute to sailing; her letters after visit, 1926 Jul - Aug (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Letters to/from extended Smith family regarding engagement and plans to go to China, 1926 Jul (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Walter to Ruth Marie
    - Acknowledges receipt of Ruth Marie's Christmas card in June 1925 with happy recollections of their meeting in England; writes of his travels, work, and mission life; by May 1926 has proposed marriage; includes copies of Walter's letters to/from Bishop Roots regarding his proposal, 1925 Jun - 1926 May (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Nearly daily letters written to Ruth Marie following her acceptance of his proposal of marriage, 1926 Jun 1-11 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Nearly daily letters to Ruth Marie including information about China, plans for wedding and housing, 1926 Jun 12-29 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Love letters in anticipation of Ruth Marie's arrival in China and wedding, 1926 Jul - Aug (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Walter traveling for his work to Hankow, Yochow, Kuling, 1926 Nov - Dec (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Ruth Marie to Walter
    - Ruth Marie planning to go to Europe when marriage proposal received by cable; begins to preparing to go to China, 1926 May - (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Ruth Marie accepted by American Church Mission, preparing for trip to China, 1926 Jun 16-28 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Love letters; preparation for trip to China; one letter written in China; fragments, 1926 Jul, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 18)
- General Correspondence, Series II
  - Letters of Walter to/from others, including fellow missionaries Robert Bundy, Bishop Logan H. Roots, 1926 Jun - 1927 Jun (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Letters of Ruth Marie to/from others, primarily in congratulations for her engagement, including from Eliza Roots, wife of Bishop Logan Roots, 1926 Jun (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Letters of others, including to Ruth Marie's mother, 1923-1926 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Writings, Series III
  - Diary of Walter Taylor, 1923-1927 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    Five-year type diary provides succinct overview of activities
  - Personal annual reports of Walter Taylor; fragment of travel account, 1924, 1926, no date (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Published articles by Walter Taylor, including "Chinese Architecture in Modern Buildings" in The Chinese Recorder, October 1924; "An Architectural Pilgrimage in China" in The American Architect, July 1929, 1924-1956 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Handwritten memoir by Ruth Marie Smith Taylor, circa 1946 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Personal Items and Memorabilia, Series IV
  - Biographical documentation, including account of romance of Walter Taylor and Ruth Marie Smith written by son Kenneth Warwick Taylor, newspaper clippings, cables, letter regarding marriage certificate, wedding invitation, lists of names, 1926, no date (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Travel mementos, including menus, receipts, passenger lists, 1923-1926 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Collected material, including District of Hankow Newsletter, Tripod newsletter (Deltas of Southern California, poems about Taylors by fellow missionaries, 1926, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Collected material, including cards, invitations, 1923, no date (Box 2, Folder 29)
- Photographs, Series V
  - Photos of Ruth Marie and Walter Taylor, including wedding and in various settings in China, 1926, no date (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Scenes and buildings in China, 1924-1926, no date (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Album pages and mounted photographs of buildings designed by Walter Taylor and other scenes, 1924-1926, no date (Box OV1)
    Buildings depicted include St. Andrew's Church and Gymnasium of Boone College, Central China University, Wuchang; Holy Trinity Church, Tokyo. Mounted brochure for "Walter A. Taylor A.I.A. Architect" lists projects for which Taylor served as architect, associated architect, or consultant.